American Eugenics Society Records 1916-1973 Mss.575.06.Am3
American Philosophical Society
American Eugenics Society Papers
1916-1973
Mss.575.06.Am3
American Philosophical Society
12.0 Linear feet
The American Eugenics Society Records is a small, selective collection offering information on various periods of the Society's development, including correspondence, membership records, and formal and informal material on its history. Of particular interest are the records of the Society's numerous committees, including the Executive Education, Population Genetics Research, Legislative, and local and state committees, and documentation of AES educational initiatives at state fairs and eugenic health exhibits and contests, especially the Fitter Family Contests. A scrapbook containing 97 images of Fitter Family and eugenic health exhibits, 1924-1926, provides valuable visual information of AES activities. One series in the collection relates to the numerous Princeton Conferences and to a genealogical survey of the populations of Shutesbury and Leverett, Massachusetts, and there is also material on the Population Council. The collection largely revolves around Frederick Osborn, the moving force in the Society for most of its later history, and it includes approximately 100 papers written or delivered by Osborn concerning eugenics, genetics, or population related topics.
American Eugenics Society.
Separated Materials note
Books and journals materials transferred to Printed Materials, including:
Eugenical News (1916-1953, except 1939)
Eugenics, A Journal of Race Betterment(1928-1931)
Eugenics Quarterly [title later changed to Social Biology] (1954-1970, except 1968, 1969, 1971)
Eugenics Review (1909-1914)
Bibliographica Eugenica(1927-1934)
Blacker, C. P., Eugenics, Galton and After
Bonar, James, Malthus and His Work
Darwin, Leonard, What is Eugenics?
A Decade of Progress in Eugenics -- Third International Congress of Eugenics
East, Edward M., Mankind at the Cross Roads
Galton, Francis, Hereditary Genius
Galton, Francis, Essays in Eugenics
Haller, Mark H., Eugenics
Hammons, Helen G., Hereditary Counseling
Holmes, Samuel J., The Trend of the Race
Huntington, Ellsworth, Tomorrow's Children
Huntington, Ellsworth, and Whitney, Leon F., The Builders of America
Laughlin, H. H., Eugenical Sterilization in the United States
Lorimer, Frank, and Osborn, Frederick, Dynamics of Population
Osborn, Frederick, Preface to Eugenics, 1940 and 1951
Osborn, Frederick, The Future of Human Heredity
Pickens, Donald K., Eugenics and the Progressive
Redfield, Casper L., Control of Heredity
Schwesinger, Gladys C., Heredity and Environment
Terman, Lewis M., Genetic Studies of Genius, vols. 1 and 2
Wiggam, Albert Edward, The Fruit of the Family Tree
Bibliography
The AES Records are briefly described in Bentley Glass, A Guide to the Genetics Collections of the American Philosophical Society (Philadelphia, 1988).
African American History Note
Eugenics was inevitably entangled in many aspects of American social and political life, and particularly in setting and supporting national policy with regard to immigration and the treatment of ethnic and racial minorities. The records in this collection may prove useful to students of African American history in this regard.
Genetics Note
This collection contains materials which relate to the history of genetics.
The AES Papers comprise 50 boxes of correspondence, manuscripts, and other materials, and include an extensive collection of photographs and a file of index cards carrying the information about a eugenic study made in Shutesbury, Massachusetts. A scrapbook entitled 'Samples' includes printed forms used by the Society, and various pamphlets. Three volumes of the Frederick Osborn correspondence are also included. These contain memos, minutes of meetings, correspondence, press clippings, and drafts of articles by Osborn. Five notebooks contain materials relating to the five conferences held at Princeton between 1964 and 1969 on the general subject of "Population Generics and Demography." There is also a loose-leaf notebook titled " AES: Position and Aims of the AES, 1961 Statement." This notebook documents the important changes in the goals and emphases of the Society beginning in the 1930s, involving a shift from hereditarian views toward a more environmentalist view. This shift was one for which Osborn himself took much credit. Garland Allen claims that this collection of the AES Papers reveals that Osborn did not change his fundamental views and was not so fully responsible for the evident decline and moderation of American eugenics during the 1930s. [See Barry Mehler and Garland E. Allen in the Mendel Newsletter 14: 9-15, 1977.]
Adams, David E. -- Eugenics, personal religion as a factor in race progress Manuscripts (11 pages) 1926-1927
Adams, Frederick F. -- Eugenics, well-born Manuscripts (8 pages) 1926-1927
American Eugenics Party Correspondence (19 items) 1962-1968
American Eugenics Society Scrapbooks (96 photographs) Circa 1923-1929
Bajema, Carl Jay Correspondence (58 items) 1965-1967
Geneticist-Demographer Training Program Correspondence (17 items) 1965-1966
Harvard Growth Study. Third Study Correspondence (59 items) 1966-1970
International Congress of Eugenics. Second Congress Records (4 items) 1921-1924
Johnson, Roswell H. Correspondence (23 items) 1927-1940
Kirkpatrick, Edwin A. Correspondence (31 items) 1927-1931
Lindbergh, Charles A. Correspondence (25 items) 1952-1972
Milbank Memorial Fund Correspondence (99 items) 1959-1972
Osborn, Frederick Henry Correspondence (178 items) 1928-1972
Population Council Correspondence (108 items) 1951-1973
Project Talent Correspondence (18 items) 1967-1969
Shutesbury-Leverett Survey Records (11 folders) 1915-1928
Society for the Study of Social Biology Records (4 folders) 1972-1974
Related Archival Materials note
See also the Frederick Henry Osborn Papers (Ms. Coll. 24).
The autobiography of Leon F. Whitney (B W613b) contains additional information on the AES.
The Charles B. Davenport Papers (B D27) contain 114 letters regarding the American Eugenics Society and its Council, and 183 letters to or from Frederick Osborn.
Images from the AES scrapbook are included in the Dolan DNA Learning Center Eugenics Archive on the Cold Spring Harbor website.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of the American Eugenics Society, through Frederick Osborn, Leon Whitney, and Jonathan Marks, 1967-1995.
Scope and Contents note
The Records of the American Eugenics Society document the varied promotional activities of the foremost organization for eugenic education and advocacy in the United States during the 1920s and 1930s. Consisting of 9 linear feet of administrative records, correspondence, and formal and informal histories of the Society, the Records span the entire history of the organization from 1921 through 1972, though weighted rather heavily toward the years before the Second World War.
The main body of records includes routine correspondence relating to AES activities and membership, including membership records from the beginning of the Society, correspondence relative to publications and orders for publications.
At the end of the collection is a file of 4x6" index cards representing a eugenic study of Shutesbury, Massachusetts, a town selected for eugenic study due to its visible decline over the previous decades and for the suspected high proportion of "degenerate" residents.
Between 1926 and 1928, the AES held contests for the best sermon preached on the subject of eugenics. In addition to the nine folders labeled AES Sermon Contest, the collection includes 45 submissions filed under the name of the minister, preached before Presbyterian, Methodist, Congregational, Baptist, Unitarian, and Jewish congregations across the country.
A particularly valuable part of the collection is the series of scrapbooks maintained by the Society. The most important of these if the photograph album containing 97 images of Eugenic Health Exhibits at the Kansas Free Fair, 1925, and in fairs in Michigan and Texas, including images of the exhibits themselves (Mendel's Theater, the flashing light exhibit, guinea pigs, and other exhibits), exterior views of the Eugenic Health buildings, images of eugenicists, including Charles B. Davenport, Judge Harry Olson and Professor Henry P. Fairchild, as well as most of the members of the AES Board of Directors over the years, and a number of images of winners of fitter family contests. The other three scrapbooks contain newspaper clippings of articles of eugenic interest, reflecting the AES effort to stay abreast of public perceptions of the field.
Many of the photographs in the scrapbook from Series II. have been digitized. Links to the digital versions of the images are included in the inventory. You may also view a gallery of all images here.
Biographical/Historical note
The Second International Conference on Eugenics, held in New York in 1921, produced one concrete result: the American Eugenics Society. Although the eugenics movement had been gaining strength in the United States for over a decade, there was at the time no formal organization through which to pursue its broader political and educational agenda. As a result, a group of prominent eugenicists founded the Eugenics Committee of the U.S.A., which became the Eugenics Society of America, and finally, in 1925, the American Eugenics Society (AES).
From its base in New Haven, Connecticut, the AES soon attracted the support of nearly every major American eugenicist and for the first decade of its existence, at least, was very successful at promoting eugenic ideas to the American public. More an advocacy group than a scientific organization, the AES promoted its ideals of racial betterment, eugenic health, and genetic education through public lectures, conferences, publications, and exhibits at county and state fairs. Among its most popular promotions were a contest for the best sermon on eugenic theme and a series of "fitter family contests" in which participants' families (divided into small, medium, and large family classes) were ranked based on information provided on the mental, physical, and moral health of family members. The AES also sponsored eugenic health exhibits, featuring such exhibits as Mendel's Theater, a presentation of basic principles of genetics and heredity, and the "flashing light exhibit," a board titled "Some people are born to be a burden to the rest," on which lights were set to blink at periodic intervals representing how often a "defective" was born in the United States (rapid blinking) and how often a "high grade" individual was born (slow blinking).
Beginning in the 1930s, the AES began a slow transformation into a less programmatic organization. This figure most often credited with bringing about this shift was Frederick Osborn, Secretary of the Society from 1928 until 1972. Osborn had a clear impact on the reformulation of AES policies and a greater focus on issues of population control, genetics, and, later, medical genetics.
During the early 1950s, the AES left New Haven for New York City, taking offices and funding from the Population Council. They remained active in promoting scientific investigation into eugenic topics, sponsoring five conferences at Princeton University between 1964 and 1969 on population genetics and demography, and drawing an international cast of scientists. In 1972, the Society was reorganized and rechristened the Society for the Study of Social Biology. Its journal, Eugenics: A Journal of Race Betterment, was renamed Social Biology.
Osborn, Frederick, 1889-1981; Population Council; Princeton Conferences; Whitney, Leon Fradley, 1894-1973; Biology, genetics, eugenics; Eugenics--Societies, etc.; Eugenics--United States; Fitter Family Contests; Genetics--Societies, etc.; Race, race relations, racism
- Series I. Correspondence and Records (Box 1-20)
  - Abbott, Lilian (Box 1)
  - Acme Newspictures, Inc. (Box 1)
  - Adams, D. N. (Box 1)
  - Adams, David E., 1926-1927 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes sermon entitled "Eugenics, personal religion as a factor in race progress" (11 pages).
    American Eugenics Society; Eugenics; Human genetics -- Race; Lectures, public speaking -- Sermons
  - Adams, Frederick F., 1926-1927 (Box 1)
    Includes sermon entitled "Eugenics, well-born" (8 pages).
    American Eugenics Society; Eugenics; Lectures, public speaking -- Sermons
  - Adams, Jeanette M. (Box 1)
  - Addison, W. H. F. (Box 1)
  - Adler, Herman N. (Box 1)
  - Adriance, V. (Box 1)
  - Affleck, B. F. (Box 1)
  - Agassiz, G. R. (Box 1)
  - Albany Public Library (Box 1)
  - Albert, Henry (Box 1)
  - Alberta, Government of the Province of, Department of Public Health (Box 1)
  - Albertson, Charles Carroll (Box 1)
  - Allen, Bennet M. (Box 1)
  - Allen, Eric W. (Box 1)
  - Allen, Truman J. (Box 1)
  - Alley, Leon A. (Box 1)
  - Allyn, Hariett M. (Box 1)
  - Altenburg, E. (Box 1)
  - American Academy of Political and Social Science (Box 1)
  - American Association for the Study of the Feebleminded (Box 1)
  - American Baptist Publication Society (Box 1)
  - American Birth Control League, Inc. (Box 1)
  - American Child Health Association (Box 1)
  - American Eugenics Party, 1962-1968; 19.0 Item(s) (Box 1)
    Eugenics; Human genetics -- Race; Political issues
  - American Eugenics Society (Box 1-12)
    - American Eugenics Society, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Account Book, 1967-1969
    - Accounts - Subscription Agencies (Box 1)
    - Advisory Council (Box 1)
    - Annual Meeting, 1937 (Box 1)
    - Archives (Box 1)
      American Philosophical Society
      Bell, Whitfield J., Jr.
      Osborn, Frederick
    - Bank of New York Account (Box 1)
    - Bequests (Box 1)
    - By-Laws: Amendments, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - By-Laws and Constitution (Box 1)
    - By-Laws, Constitution, Certificates of Incorporation, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Catechism of Eugenics (Box 1)
      - Requests #1-5, 5 folders (Box 1)
      - Requests #6-17, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Circulars (Box 1)
      Fair Associations
      State Committees
      Daughters of the American Revolution
      Student Workers
      Follow up form for Recommended Members
      Social Workers
    - Committee on Finance and Membership (Box 1)
    - Committee on Legislation (Box 1)
    - Conferences (Box 1)
      - Conference of Differential Reproduction, 1970 (Box 1)
      - Conference on Education and Eugenics, 1937 (Box 1)
      - Conference on Eugenics and Birth Control (Box 1)
      - Conference on the Eugenic Aspects of Housing (Box 1)
      - Conference on Eugenics in Relation to Nursing, 1937 (Box 1)
      - Conference on Human Evolution, 1971; 4 folders (Box 1)
      - Conference on Medicine and Eugenics, 1937 (Box 1)
      - Conference on Publicists, 1937 (Box 1)
      - Conference on the Relation of Eugenics and the Church, 1939 (Box 1)
      - Conferences - Recreation and the Use of Leisure Time, 1937 (Box 1)
    - Contribution from Members (Box 1)
    - Contributions to Other Organizations, 1953 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1964-1973; 75 folders (Box 2-4)
      - Correspondence, September 1964-March 1965 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, April-June 1965 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, August-November 1965 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, December 1965-January 1966 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, February-March 1966 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, April 1966 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, May 1966 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, June-August 1966 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, September-October 1966 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, November 1966 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, December 1966 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, January 1967 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, February 1967 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, March 1967 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, April 1967 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, May 1967 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, June 1967 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, July-August 1967 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, September 1967 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, October 1967 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, November 1967 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, December 1967 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, January 1968 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, February 1968 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, March 1968 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, April 1968 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, May 1968 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, June-August 1968 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, September 1968 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, October 1968 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, November 1968 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, December 1968 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, January 1969 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, February 1969 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, March 1969 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, April 1969 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, May 1969 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, June 1969 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, July-August 1969 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, September 1969 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, October 1969 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, November 1969 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, December 1969 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, January 1970 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, February 1970 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, March 1970 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, April 1970 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, May 1970 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, June 1970 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, July 1970 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, September 1970 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, October 1970 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, November 1970 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, December 1970 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, January 1971 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, February 1971 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, March 1971 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, April 1971 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, May 1971 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, June 1971 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, July-August 1971 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, September 1971 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, October 1971 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, November 1971 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, December 1971 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, January 1972 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, February 1972 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, March 1972 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, April 1972 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, May-June 1972 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, July-September 1972 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, October-December 1972 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, January-February 1973 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, March-April 1973 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, May-June 1973 (Box 4)
    - "Crack-Pot" Literature, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Director's Correspondence in re 1961 Statement of Purposes, 6 folders (Box 5)
    - Eugenics Committee, Minutes, 1922-1925; 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Fairs - Exhibits (Box 5)
    - Fellowship applications (Box 5)
    - Fellowships (Box 5)
    - Financial Statements, n.d.; 1953-1971; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Fitter Family Contest (Box 5)
    - Florida Committee (Box 5)
    - Genealogical Survey (Box 5)
    - Grants Awarded, 1961 (Box 5)
    - History (Box 5)
    - Indiana Committee (Box 5)
    - Iowa Committee (Box 5)
    - Legal Papers, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Medical Genetics Committee (Box 6)
      - Medical Genetics Committee, 5 folders (Box 6)
      - Medical Genetics Committee - Minutes of Meetings (Box 6)
    - Medical Genetics Grants (Box 6)
      - Medical Genetics Grants, 5 folders (Box 6)
      - Medical Gentics Grants, 1961; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Membership Campaign (Box 6-7)
      - Membership Campaign, 1923 (Box 6)
      - Membership Campaign, 1924 (Box 6)
      - Membership Campaign, 1925 (Box 6)
      - Membership Campaign (A-C) by surname, 1927 (Box 6)
      - Membership Campaign (D-F) by surname, 1927 (Box 6)
      - Membership Campaign (G-J) by surname, 1927 (Box 6)
      - Membership Campaign (K-M) by surname, 1927 (Box 6)
      - Membership Campaign (N-R) by surname, 1927 (Box 6)
      - Membership Campaign (S-Z) by surname, 1927 (Box 6)
      - Membership Campaign, 1928 (Box 6)
      - Membership Campaign (A-C) by state, 1930 (Box 7)
      - Membership Campaign (D-I) by state, 1930 (Box 7)
      - Membership Campaign (J-L) by state, 1930 (Box 7)
      - Membership Campaign (M) by state, 1930 (Box 7)
      - Membership Campaign (N) by state, 1930 (Box 7)
      - Membership Campaign (O-R) by state, 1930 (Box 7)
      - Membership Campaign (S-Z) by state, 1930 (Box 7)
      - Membership Campaign (A-Z) by state, 1930 (Box 7)
      - Membership Campaign (A-E) by surname, 1930 (Box 7)
      - Membership Campaign (F-L) by surname, 1930 (Box 7)
      - Membership Campaign (M-R) by surname, 1930 (Box 7)
      - Membership Campaign (S-Z) by surname, 1930 (Box 7)
      - Membership Campaign, Miscellany (Box 7)
    - Minutes (Box 7)
      - Minutes, 1925-1935; 3 folders (Box 7)
      - Minutes, 1936-1937; 4 folders (Box 7)
      - Minutes, 1938-1956 (Box 7)
      - Minutes of Meetings (Box 7)
    - Name Change (Box 7)
    - New Hampshire Committee (Box 7)
    - New Jersey Committee (Box 7)
    - Pennsylvania Committee (Box 7)
      Collins, H. H.
      Emlen, Samuel
      Baker, Horace F.
      Dunn, Matthew A.
    - Pledge of Support, Requests for (Box 7)
    - Popular Education Committee (Box 7)
    - Population Genetics Research Committee (Box 8)
      - Population Genetics Research Committee (Box 8)
      - Population Genetics Research Committee -- Correspondence, 1966-1968; 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Population Genetics Research Committee -- Meeting Notices, 1966-1968 (Box 8)
      - Population Genetics Research Committee -- Proposals, 1966-1968 (Box 8)
    - Princeton Conferences (Box 8-11)
      - Princeton Conferences, 1966-1968 (Box 8)
      - Princeton Conferences, 1st, 1964; 4 folders (Box 8)
      - Princeton Conferences, 1st -- Transcripts, 1964; 14 folders (Box 8)
      - Princeton Conferences, 2nd, June 1962-January 1966; 5 folders (Box 8)
      - Princeton Conferences, 2nd -- Papers, 1962; 5 folders (Box 9)
      - Princeton Conferences, 2nd -- Transcripts, 1962; 11 folders (Box 9)
      - Princeton Conferences, 3rd, 1966; 4 folders (Box 9)
      - Princeton Conferences, 3rd -- Papers, 1966 (Box 9)
      - Princeton Conferences, 3rd -- Transcripts, 1966; 11 folders (Box 10)
      - Princeton Conferences, 3rd -- Transcripts (copy), 1966; 6 folders (Box 10)
      - Princeton Conferences, 4th, 1967; 6 folders (Box 10)
        Papers by James F. Crow, Bruce K. Eckland, Claude V. Kiser, and Robert J. Garrison et al. on assortative mating
      - Princeton Conferences, 4th -- Papers, 1967; 2 folders (Box 10)
      - Princeton Conferences, 4th -- Transcripts #1-5, 1967; 5 folders (Box 10)
      - Princeton Conferences, 4th -- Transcripts #6-11, 1967; 6 folders (Box 11)
      - Princeton Conferences, 5th, 1969 (Box 11)
      - Princeton Conferences, 5th - Abstracts, 1969; 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Princeton Conferences, 5th - Transcripts, 1969; 11 folders (Box 11)
    - Printing Orders, 1926-1942; 15 folders (Box 11)
      Pamphlets, promotional material, etc., printed for the AES. Originally bound into a scrapbook.
    - Program in Genetics and Population Characteristics, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - Publicity (Box 12)
    - Requests for Grants (Box 12)
    - Requests for Grants, Refused (Box 12)
    - Royalities, 4 folders (Box 12)
    - Royalities from Lindzey et al. (Box 12)
    - Scrapbook -- See album at end of collection (Box 12)
    - Securities, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - Sermon Contest (Box 12)
      - Sermon Contest, 1926; 7 folders (Box 12)
      - Sermon Contest, 1928; 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Southern California Branch Records, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - Southern California Branch, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - State and Local Committees, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - Symposium on Heredity Counseling (Box 12)
    - Treasurer's Report (Box 12)
  - American Frame and Picture Co., Inc. (Box 13)